Anna Barth

Columbia University, Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory
Doctoral student, Department of Earth & Environmental Sciences
(646) 887 5993 • barthac@gmail.com • barthac.github.io

Research interests

My research interests focus on the generation, evolution and dynamics of magma beneath volcanoes. In particular, how do crystal-rich magmas respond to magma injections from below? How are eruptions triggered? What controls eruption style? To investigate these questions my research integrates petrological data and field observations with fluid dynamical modelling and analogue experiments. An integral aspect of this work is developing new methods for conveying multivariate data using sonification and visualisation, with applications for public outreach, teaching, and scientific research.

Education

Dec 2020 (expected)	Ph.D. Earth & Envi. Sci	Columbia University
2017	M.Phil. Earth & Envi. Sci	Columbia University
2015	M.Sc. Geological Sciences (top of class)	University of Cambridge
2014	B.Sc. Natural Sciences, First Class	University of Cambridge

Research experience

2015 – present	Ph.D. thesis advised by Dr. Terry Plank using volatiles to understand the	
	dynamics of magma ascent during explosive eruptions	
2014 - 2015	Master's project supervised by Dr. Andy Woods and Dr. Marie Edmonds looking	
	at the migration of gas through crystal mushes	
2010	Laboratory experiments on materials with a negative poisson's ratio with Katia	
	Bertoldi at the Material Sciences Laboratory in Harvard	
2010	Assisting Mark Lancaster in the Particle Physics group at UCL	

Teaching experience

2020 – present	Founding member of team designing course on intersection of Climate Change
	and Racism (GR9810) at Columbia University
2019 – present	Unofficial TA for Sonic and Visual Representation of Data (MUSIGR6602) at
	Columbia University (developed python code and helped students with projects.)
2017 – present	Mentor for undergraduate students Dylan Bogoevski & Sarah Shi
2018	TA for Geochemistry for a Habitable Planet (UN3101) at Columbia University
2018	TA for Field Geology (UN3010) at Columbia University
2016	TA for Solid Earth (W2200) at Columbia University

Outreach & Service

2020	Judge for AGU Michael H. Freilich Student Visualization Competition
2015 – present	Education demonstration leader - Lamont's Open House and Columbia's Girls'
	Science Day

2016 – present	Organiser of Research as Art – annual exhibit of the creative endeavours of the
	Lamont research community
2017	Organiser of Storke student fieldtrip to the Azores
2016-2017	Geochemistry seminar organizer

Honours & Awards

2019	Grand Prize in the NASA Data Visualisation and Storytelling Competition
	(consequently I was invited to give a presentation using the Nasa Hyperwall at
	AGU Fall Meeting 2019)
2018	Outstanding Student Presentation Award, AGU Fall Meeting
2015	VMSG meeting, Norwich, UK, Jan 2015: Prize for best poster of the session and
	best student poster of the conference
2015	First place in UK-wide Neftex Earth Model Award for Masters thesis
2015	Martin Jacks Prize from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge
2015	Harkness Prize for graduating top of class, Earth Sciences Dept., Cambridge
2014	Samuel Taylor Scholarship for Natural Sciences by Sidney Sussex College
2014	BPI summer research bursary
2013	Travel grant to visit the ophiolite in Gros Morne National Park, Newfoundland
2013	Research grant for mapping project in Fogo Island, Newfoundland.
	_ ** ** /

Computational skills

Python, MATLAB, ArcGIS, Adobe Creative Suite

Peer-Reviewed Publications

Barth A., Plank, T., (Submitted to Frontiers in Earth Science) The ins and outs of water in olivine-hosted melt inclusions: hygrometer vs speedometer.

Barth A., Karlstrom, L., Holtzman, B., Niyak, A., Paté, A (*Accepted to Computer Music Journal, MIT Press*). Sonification and animation of multivariate data illuminates geyser eruption dynamics.

Newcombe, M., Plank, T., Zhang, Y., Holycross, M., **Barth, A**., Lloyd, A., Ferguson, D., Hauri, E., (2020) Magma Pressure-Temperature-time paths during mafic explosive eruptions. Frontiers in Earth Science.

Newcombe, M., Plank, T., **Barth, A.**, Asimow, P., Hauri, E. (2019). Water-in-olivine magma ascent chronometry: Every crystal is a clock. Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research, 106872.

Barth, A., Newcombe, M., Plank, T., Gonnermann, H., Hajimirza, S., Soto, G. J., & Hauri, E. (2019). Magma decompression rate correlates with explosivity at basaltic volcanoes—Constraints from water diffusion in olivine. Journal of Volcanology and Geothermal Research, 387, 106664.

Barth, A., Edmonds, M., & Woods, A. (2019). Valve-like dynamics of gas flow through a packed crystal mush and cyclic strombolian explosions. Scientific reports, 9(1), 821.

Donaldson, C., Sood, R., **Barth, A**., Christie, H., & Kerr, A. C. (2015). Geological relationships in northwestern Fogo Island and their implications for the timing of orogenic events. Newfoundland Department of Natural Resources, Geological Survey, Report 2015-1, 27-42. Report, 15(1), 27-42.